<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Muneeb Sultan</title>
    <link>msultan.github.io/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Muneeb Sultan</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016 Mohammad Muneeb Sultan</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>tICA-Metadynamics: Accelerating Metadynamics by Using Kinetically Selected Collective Variables.</title>
      <link>/msultan.github.io/publication/ticameta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/msultan.github.io/publication/ticameta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Metadynamics is a powerful enhanced molecular
dynamics sampling method that accelerates simulations by
adding history-dependent multidimensional Gaussians along
selective collective variables (CVs). In practice, choosing a
small number of slow CVs remains challenging due to the
inherent high dimensionality of biophysical systems. Here we
show that time-structure based independent component
analysis (tICA), a recent advance in Markov state model
literature, can be used to identify a set of variationally optimal
slow coordinates for use as CVs for Metadynamics. We show
that linear and nonlinear tICA-Metadynamics can complement existing MD studies by explicitly sampling the system’s slowest
modes and can even drive transitions along the slowest modes even when no such transitions are observed in unbiased
simulations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kinase simulations</title>
      <link>/msultan.github.io/project/kinases/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/msultan.github.io/project/kinases/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kinase&#34;&gt;Kinases&lt;/a&gt; are large family of protein found in a variety of cells that catalyze
the transfer of ATP&amp;rsquo;s gamma phosphate group to target substrate. They initiate and control a large number of
cellular pathways and are critical pharmaceutical targets. My research involves looking at the relationship between the
sequence and dynamics of these kinases. The fundamental question that I would like to answer is what happens to the
kinase&amp;rsquo;s underlying free energy landscape when its amino acid sequence is mutated, similar to mutations found in many
cancers.
To answer these questions, I am employing MD simulations combined with a new variation to MSMs which allows us to
explicitly compare the kinetics and thermodynamics of these mutants. I have simulated over 12 milliseconds in aggregate
data with three publications under preparation. These simulations are the largest set of kinase simulations
ever performed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adblock and Hugo&#39;s academic theme</title>
      <link>/msultan.github.io/post/adblock-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/msultan.github.io/post/adblock-hugo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I learnt rather painfully, using adblockers on Hugo&amp;rsquo;s academic theme can
block &lt;a href=&#34;http://fontawesome.io/&#34;&gt;Font Awesome&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s icons from properly showing up
 underneath my picture. The fastest solution for now seems to be white listing
 the website.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software Development</title>
      <link>/msultan.github.io/project/software/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/msultan.github.io/project/software/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am current involved in the active development of several software packages related to
Markov modeling including &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/msmbuilder/msmbuilder&#34;&gt;MSMbuilder&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/msmbuilder/osprey&#34;&gt;Osprey&lt;/a&gt;.
I also extensively use &lt;a href=&#34;pande.stanford.edu&#34;&gt;our lab&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s distributed computing platform &lt;a href=&#34;http://foldingathome.stanford.edu/&#34;&gt;Folding@home&lt;/a&gt;,
and am the first user of our &lt;a href=&#34;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.sonymobile.androidapp.gridcomputing&amp;amp;hl=en&#34;&gt;mobile client&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advanced Sampling</title>
      <link>/msultan.github.io/project/sampling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/msultan.github.io/project/sampling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been interested in using MSM to extend the capability of MD simulations. The fundamental question I am
interested in answering if whether we can reduce the computational complexity of a new simulation by leveraging
information from the current MSM. The new simulation could be a new sequence, a new physics model or perhaps
some post translational modification. To that end, I am borrowing ideas from Reinforcement-Learning and Markov decision
processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I showed over &lt;a href=&#34;http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/acs.jctc.7b00182&#34;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2017/07/02/158592&#34;&gt;series&lt;/a&gt;
 of papers that the &lt;a href=&#34;http://msmbuilder.org/3.8.0/decomposition.html#tica&#34;&gt;tICA&lt;/a&gt; algorithm can be used to
form better CV than human intuition in enhanced sampling algorithms such as Metadynamics/Umbrella sampling. This is&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimized parameter selection reveals trends in Markov state models for protein folding</title>
      <link>/msultan.github.io/publication/optimizedfolding/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/msultan.github.io/publication/optimizedfolding/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As molecular dynamics simulations access increasingly longer time scales, complementary advances in the analysis of
biomolecular time-series data are necessary. Markov state models offer a powerful framework for this analysis by
describing a system’s states and the transitions between them. A recently established variational theorem for Markov
state models now enables modelers to systematically determine the best way to describe a system’s dynamics. In the
context of the variational theorem, we analyze ultra-long folding simulations for a canonical set of twelve proteins
[K. Lindorff-Larsen et al., Science 334, 517 (2011)] by creating and evaluating many types of Markov state models.
We present a set of guidelines for constructing Markov state models of protein folding; namely, we recommend the use
of cross-validation and a kinetically motivated dimensionality reduction step for improved descriptions of folding
dynamics. We also warn that precise kinetics predictions rely on the features chosen to describe the system and pose
the description of kinetic uncertainty across ensembles of models as an open issue.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MSMBuilder: Statistical Models for Biomolecular Dynamics</title>
      <link>/msultan.github.io/publication/msmb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/msultan.github.io/publication/msmb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;MSMBuilder is a software package for building statistical models of high-dimensional time-series data. It is
 designed with a particular focus on the analysis of atomistic simulations of biomolecular dynamics such as protein
 folding and conformational change. MSMBuilder is named for its ability to construct Markov State Models (MSMs),
 a class of models that has gained favor among computational biophysicists. In addition to both well-established and
 newer MSM methods, the package includes complementary algorithms for understanding time-series data such as hidden
 Markov models (HMMs) and time-structure based independent component analysis (tICA). MSMBuilder boasts an easy to
 use command-line interface, as well as clear and consistent abstractions through its Python API (application
 programming interface). MSMBuilder is developed with careful consideration for compatibility with the broader
  machine-learning community by following the design of scikit-learn. The package is used primarily by practitioners
  of molecular dynamics but is just as applicable to other computational or experimental time-series measurements.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Osprey: Hyperparameter Optimization for Machine Learning</title>
      <link>/msultan.github.io/publication/osprey/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/msultan.github.io/publication/osprey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Osprey is a tool for hyperparameter optimization of machine learning algorithms in Python. Hyperparameter optimization
can often be an onerous process for researchers, due to time-consuming experimental replicates, non-convex objective
 functions, and constant tension between exploration of global parameter space and local optimization (Jones, Schonlau,
  and Welch 1998). We&amp;rsquo;ve designed Osprey to provide scientists with a practical, easy-to-use way of finding optimal
  model parameters. The software works seamlessly with scikit-learn estimators (Pedregosa et al. 2011) and supports
  many different search strategies for choosing the next set of parameters with which to evaluate a given model,
  including gaussian processes (GPy 2012), tree-structured Parzen estimators (Yamins, Tax, and Bergstra 2013),
  as well as random and grid search. As hyperparameter optimization is an embarrassingly parallel problem, Osprey
  can easily scale to hundreds of concurrent processes by executing a simple command-line program multiple times.
  This makes it easy to exploit large resources available in high-performance computing environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Osprey is actively maintained by researchers at Stanford University and other institutions around the world. While
originally developed to analyze computational protein dynamics (McGibbon, Harrigan, et al. 2016), it is applicable to
any scikit-learn-compatible pipeline. The source code for Osprey is hosted on GitHub and has been archived to Zenodo
(McGibbon, Hernández, et al. 2016). Full documentation can be found at &lt;a href=&#34;http://msmbuilder.org/osprey&#34;&gt;http://msmbuilder.org/osprey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ML &amp; MSMs</title>
      <link>/msultan.github.io/project/machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/msultan.github.io/project/machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am currently interested in the problem of extending Markov state models to multiple sequences. The generic
question that I am trying to answer is how do we best compare the kinetics and thermodynamics of two differing
kinase sequences.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Automatic selection of order parameters in the analysis of large scale molecular dynamics simulations</title>
      <link>/msultan.github.io/publication/treeclf/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/msultan.github.io/publication/treeclf/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Given the large number of crystal structures and NMR ensembles that have been solved to date, classical molecular
 dynamics (MD) simulations have become powerful tools in the atomistic study of the kinetics and thermodynamics of
 biomolecular systems on ever increasing time scales. By virtue of the high-dimensional conformational state space
 that is explored, the interpretation of large-scale simulations faces difficulties not unlike those in the big data
 community. We address this challenge by introducing a method called clustering based feature selection (CB-FS) that
 employs a posterior analysis approach. It combines supervised machine learning (SML) and feature selection with Markov
 state models to automatically identify the relevant degrees of freedom that separate conformational states. We
 highlight the utility of the method in the evaluation of large-scale simulations and show that it can be used for
 the rapid and automated identification of relevant order parameters involved in the functional transitions of two
 exemplary cell-signaling proteins central to human disease states.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Protein Dynamics with L1-Regularized Reversible Hidden Markov Models</title>
      <link>/msultan.github.io/publication/hmm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/msultan.github.io/publication/hmm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We present a machine learning framework for modeling protein dynamics. Our approach uses L1-regularized, reversible
hidden Markov models to understand large protein datasets generated via molecular dynamics simulations. Our model is
motivated by three design principles: (1) the requirement of massive scalability; (2) the need to adhere to relevant physical law; and (3) the necessity of providing accessible interpretations, critical
for both cellular biology and rational drug design. We present an EM algorithm for learning and introduce a model
selection criteria based on the physical notion of convergence in relaxation timescales. We contrast our model with
standard methods in biophysics and demonstrate improved robustness. We implement our algorithm on GPUs and apply
the method to two large protein simulation datasets generated respectively on the NCSA Bluewaters supercomputer
and the Folding@Home distributed computing network. Our analysis identifies the conformational dynamics of the
ubiquitin protein critical to cellular signaling, and elucidates the stepwise activation mechanism of the c-Src
kinase protein.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Electrostatic Effects on Proton Coupled Electron Transfer in Oxomanganese Complexes Inspired by the Oxygen-Evolving Complex of Photosystem II</title>
      <link>/msultan.github.io/publication/psii/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/msultan.github.io/publication/psii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The influence of electrostatic interactions on the free energy of proton coupled electron transfer in biomimetic
oxomanganese complexes inspired by the oxygen-evolving complex (OEC) of photosystem II (PSII) are investigated.
The reported study introduces an enhanced multiconformer continuum electrostatics (MCCE) model, parametrized at
the density functional theory (DFT) level with a classical valence model for the oxomanganese core. The calculated
pKa’s and oxidation midpoint potentials (Em’s) match experimental values for eight complexes, indicating that purely
 electrostatic contributions account for most of the observed couplings between deprotonation and oxidation state
 transitions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Allosteric pathways in imidazole glycerol phosphate synthase</title>
      <link>/msultan.github.io/publication/allopath/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/msultan.github.io/publication/allopath/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Protein allosteric pathways are investigated in the imidazole glycerol phosphate synthase heterodimer in an effort to
elucidate how the effector (PRFAR, N′-[(5′-phosphoribulosyl)formimino]-5-aminoimidazole-4-carboxamide ribonucleotide)
activates glutaminase catalysis at a distance of 25 Å from the glutamine-binding site. We apply solution NMR techniques
and community analysis of dynamical networks, based on mutual information of correlated protein motions in the active
and inactive enzymes. We find evidence that the allosteric pathways in the PRFAR bound enzyme involve conserved residues
that correlate motion of the PRFAR binding loop to motion at the protein-protein interface, and ultimately at the
glutaminase active site. The imidazole glycerol phosphate synthase bienzyme is an important branch point for the histidine
and nucleotide biosynthetic pathways and represents a potential therapeutic target against microbes. The proposed
allosteric mechanism and the underlying allosteric pathways provide fundamental insights for the design of new allosteric
drugs and/or alternative herbicides.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
